Hello, and welcome to Lesson 8 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
您好，欢迎来到Wolfram U的微积分入门课程第8课。
Our topic for today is the derivative as a function.
今天我们的主题是作为函数的导数。
Let’s begin with a brief overview of today’s lesson. In Lesson 7, you learned about
让我们从今天课程的简要概述开始。
finding the derivatives at particular points for a function. Now the fact is that
在第7课中，您学习了如何在函数的特定点处计算导数。 现在的事实是
you can go beyond that and the derivative itself can be regarded as a function.
您可以超越此范围，并将导数本身视为函数。
Starting with a function, you can find the derivative, and then that gives you another function.
从一个函数开始，您可以计算导数，然后再给您另一个函数。
The way to do that in the Wolfram Language is to use to the function D. Let’s say you have
在Wolfram语言中执行此操作的方法是使用函数 D。假设您在此处
a function f[x] like over here. You can work out the derivative using D, and you get back
有函数 f[x]。您可以使用 D 求出导数，然后返回
another function. Now you can plot the function and the derivative on the same plot,
另一个函数。现在，您可以在同一图上绘制函数和导数，
and you get back this picture of the function in blue and its derivative in orange.
蓝色为函数，橙色为它的导数。
The point over here is that the derivative is a function just like the earlier one,
此处的要点是，导函数就像之前遇到过的函数一样
and you can keep on doing the same process, and that’s the plan for today, to talk about
，您可以对导函数做与普通函数相同的事情，这就是今天要讨论的
derivatives as functions and higher derivatives.
作为函数的导数和高阶导数。
Okay. A simple example. Let’s say I ask you to find the derivative of x^3 + x.
好的。 一个简单的例子。 假设我要您计算 x^3 + x 的导数。
You can work out the derivatives in D—that’s 3x^2 + 1—and then you can also use f'[x].
您可以在函数 D 中计算导数为 (3x^2 +1)，还可以使用 f'[x] 的写法。
that’s another way to do the same thing. You can plot the function derivative
这是做同样事情的另一种方式。
and you get back the result, which is the plot for both these functions. Now the difficulty is that
您可以绘制函数导数，然后返回结果，这是这两个函数的图。现在的困难是
there are many ways to write derivatives. Let’s talk a little bit about derivative notation.
有很多写导数的方法。让我们谈谈导数符号。
Some people prefer to write f[x] for the function then f'[x] for the derivative. Others prefer D.
有些人更喜欢将函数编写为 f[x]，导数编写为 f'[x]。 其他人更喜欢 D 的写法。
Some prefer y’, some use dy/dx, some use df/dx, et cetera. In fact, mathematicians like
有些人喜欢 y'，有些人使用 dy/dx，有些人使用 df/dx
to think of D and d/dx as being as being differentiation operators which work on functions
，等等。 实际上，数学家喜欢将 D 和 d/dx 视为是处理函数的微分算子。
and give you their derivatives. The whole process of calculating derivatives is called differentiation.
微分算子会给出函数的导数 计算导数的整个过程称为微分。
There is a lot of terminology over here, but as far as we are concerned, if you know D and f',
这里有很多术语，但是就我们而言，如果您知道 D 和 f'，
that’s good enough for you. So here I’ve got D[f[x]] and f'[x], and you get back
就足够了。 所以在这里，我有 D [f[x]] 和 f'[x]
just the same result in both the cases. For this lesson, if you know D and f',
在两种情况下返回相同的结果。在本课程中，如果您知道 D 和 f'，
that’s enough to do all the calculations.
足以进行所有计算。
Okay. One issue with derivatives is that they are defined by limits. If they are limits,
好的。 导数的一个问题是它们是由极限定义的。 如果是极限，
and because you can talk about left-hand and right-hand limits, you can also talk about
并且因为您可以谈论左侧和右侧极限，所以您也可以谈论
left-hand and right-hand derivatives at a point. Here’s a function g
一个点的左导数和右导数。 这是一个函数 g
defined using the RealAbs function, the absolute value function, and clearly there will be
使用 RealAbs 函数定义的绝对值函数，显然在 5 处符号会发生变化。
an issue at 5 where the sign changes. If you find the derivatives from the right and left at 5,
如果您在 5 处从左侧和右侧求导数，
then what you see is that they are different, so you have a problem
那么你会看到它们是不同的，所以这里有一个问题
because the left-hand and right-hand derivatives at the point 5 do not agree.
因为在点 5 的左导数和右导数不一致。
If you plot the function derivative, you see a little more clearly. That’s the original function,
如果您绘制函数导数，您会更加清楚地看到。
and the derivative is 3 on the right and −3 on the left. That’s one way in which things can go wrong,
那是原始函数，导数在右侧是 3，在左侧是 -3。这是会出问题的一种情况，
namely that the left-hand limit and the right-hand limit do not agree,
即左极限和右极限不一致，
and you do not have a derivative at that point.
所以在那一点没有导数。
Let’s talk about differentiability. A function is differentiable if f'[a] exists for a point a,
让我们谈谈函数的可导性。如果在点 a 上存在 f'[a]
and of course if you were to have a whole range of values from a to b, then it’s differentiable
那么函数是在这一点是可导的，当然，如果在整个区间的所有点从 a 到 b，都是可导的
if it’s differentiable at every point, every number in that interval. Here’s a function.
那么函数在该区间可导。这是一个函数。
Let’s find the derivative. The question is where is it differentiable? Well, the only difficulty
让我们求导数。问题是它在哪里是可导的？
would be at 0 because then you have a 0 in the denominator over here, and in fact,
好吧，唯一的困难就是 0 点，因为那边的分母为0，实际上，
if you work out the left- and right-hand derivatives at this point at 0, then you do see
如果您在此时计算左导数和右导数为0，那么您会看到
that they are very different. In fact if you plug in 0 into f'[x], you get back an indeterminate answer.
他们是非常不同的。 实际上，如果将 0 代入 f'[x]，您将得到一个不确定的答案。
Here’s a function which we just showed you which is differentiable everywhere except at 0.
这是我们刚刚向您展示的函数，除了 0 以外，该函数在其他地方都是可导的。
The question arises in what way can a function be non-differentiable? When can things go wrong?
问题是函数什么情况下不可导？ 什么时候会出错？
One way that they can go wrong is if you’re at a corner. Here’s an example.
他们可能会出错的一种情况是在函数的拐角处。 这是一个例子。
You have the absolute value function times 3, and if you plot it with the derivative, you see that at 0
您将绝对值函数乘以3，如果画出导函数，则会看到在 0 点
the calculation and graph both show that you have a problem at 0. You have a corner over there
计算和图像均表明有问题。您在那儿有一个角，这导致函数不可导。
which leads to the differentiability being lost. Here’s a corner for the function,
函数上的角
and that’s an issue for differentiability. Another thing that can go wrong is that you are at a cusp.
会导致函数的不可谓。可能出错的另一种情况是您处于尖峰处。
Here’s a cube root function, and at 0 again the problem is because you actually have a cusp.
这是一个立方根函数，在 0 点再次出现问题，因为您实际上有一个尖峰。
That’s a cusp over there, a change in shape, and that’s going to cause you problems with derivatives.
那是个尖峰，形状发生剧变，这会给求导带来问题。
You can see the derivative does not exist at 0.
您可以看到导数不存在 0 点。
A third way in which things can go wrong is if you are at a discontinuity of a function.
出错的第三种情况是如果您处于某个函数的不连续状态。
Here’s a function. It’s piecewise, and it changes form at 0. That’s the function.
这是一个函数。 它是分段的，并且在 0 点变了形式。
Work out the derivative, and its 0 is a problem. You get indeterminate. If you plot it,
计算出导数，在 0 点有问题。导函数值变得不确定。
you can see quite clearly that everything’s fine everywhere except at 0.
如果将其绘制出来，您会清楚地看到，除 0 以外，其他所有地方都很好。
One last thing that can go wrong is if you are at a vertical tangent. Here’s the cube root function again,
可能出错的最后一种情况是，如果您处在垂直切线上。
and if we look at 0, you actually have a problem because you have a vertical tangent over there.
再次是立方根函数，如果我们看 0 点，则实际上存在问题，因为那里有垂直切线。
That’s the way in which things can go wrong, but for the most part, functions will be differentiable,
这就是出错的所有情况，但是在大多数情况下，函数是可导的，
and if they are not, it will only happen at a few isolated points.
如果函数不可导，则只会在几个孤立的点不可导。
Now starting with a function, you cannot just work out the first derivative like over here,
现在从一个函数开始，您不仅可以算出一阶导数，
but you can go a step further and work out the second derivative. The second derivative is
您可以更进一步，算出二阶导数。二阶导数是
the derivative of the first derivative. We with start with 4x^3. You get 12x^2 and then you get 24x,
一阶导数的导数。 我们从 4x^3 开始。 得到 12x^2，然后得到 24 x,
and you can get the same result by using D with this notation, which says differentiate f
通过使用 D 的编写方式可以得到相同的结果，表示对f
with respect to x two times, and you get back just the same answer. That’s the shorthand
关于  x  求两次导，您会得到相同的答案。
for computing the second derivative. Here are the plots of all three. There’s f, there’s the first derivative
这是计算二阶导数的简写。 这是三个函数图像。f, 一阶导数
and the second derivative. The point is starting from a function, you can work out the derivative.
和二阶导数 重点是从函数出发，您可以算出导数。
Then you can work its derivative, and they are all just as good as functions.
然后，您可以对其进行求导，它们跟函数的性质一样好。
Now of course you can go on with that, and in the Wolfram Language you can work out the nth derivative
现在，您当然可以继续进行下去了，在 Wolfram 语言中，您可以算出第 n 阶导数
for any value of n, whether it be 1 or 2 or 6 or 100 or whatever. Here’s a simple function x^6.
n 可以取任何值，无论是 1 还是 2 或 6 还是 100 或其他任何值。 这是一个简单的函数 x^6。
You can work out the first six derivatives. The first expression over here is just the function itself,
您可以算出前六个导数。
and the last one is 720, which means that you are almost at the edge
这里的第一个表达式只是函数本身，最后一个表达式是 720，这意味着您已经处于
where things are going to start becoming 0. Okay. Here’s a plot of the first six derivatives.
高阶导数为 0 的前一步了。好的。这是前六个导数的图。
You have the function over here, first derivative, second derivative, et cetera.
您在此处具有一阶导数，二阶导数等函数。
You can see over here that the nth derivative is a function just like the earlier one.
您可以在这里看到第 n 个导数是一个函数，就像前一个函数一样。
Okay. Now in physics, there are some special names for nth derivatives.
好的。现在，在物理学中，第 n 个导数有一些特殊的名称。
Here’s a position function s[t], and if you work out the first six derivatives, they’ve got names.
这是位置函数 s[t]，如果您计算出前六个导数，它们就会有名称。
They’re called the velocity, the acceleration, the jerk, snap, crackle, pop.
它们被称为速度，加速度，急动度，sanp，crackle，pop。
That’s first derivative, second derivative, third derivative, fourth, fifth and sixth.
这是一阶导数，二阶导数，三阶导数，第四，第五和第六阶导数。
If you plot them, then just like in the earlier case you get back a plot, but now this shows you
如果对它们进行绘制，则就像在较早的情况下一样，您可以获得图像，
the variation of the position and velocity, et cetera as time goes by.
但是现在这可以显示位置和速度等随时间的变化。
High derivatives are really quite useful. They occur in physics, they occur elsewhere
高阶导数确实非常有用。它们存在于物理学中，它们也存在于其他地方
and in fact they are what makes calculus so applicable in real life.
实际上，正是这些因素使微积分在现实生活中如此适用。
Okay. Now we’re at the end of today’s lesson, and what you’ve learned is that you can
好的。现在我们到了本课的最后，您学到的是，不仅可以
work out derivatives not just at points, but for entire functions, and what you get then is
在各个点上求出导数，而且可以为整个函数求出导函数，然后得到的是
a new function. Because a derivative is a limit, you can compute left and right derivatives.
一个新函数。 由于导数是极限，因此您可以计算左右导数。
Now if it happens that the left and right derivatives are not equal, then the derivative
现在，如果左右导数不相等，则导数在给定点不存在。
does not exist at the given point. If it does exist, then the function is differentiable at that point.
如果确实存在，则该函数在那点是可导的。
You’ve got differentiable functions and non-differentiable functions which can occur in many ways,
您可以得到可导的函数和不可导的函数，不可导函数有多种
like you are at a corner, you are at a cusp, et cetera. As I said earlier on,
例如在函数拐角处，在尖峰处等等。
most functions will be differentiable almost everywhere. Now you can go a step further from derivatives
正如我之前说的，大多数函数几乎在任何地方都是可导的。现在您可以从导数出发更进一步
and work out higher-order derivatives—the first, second, third, fourth, et cetera—
并计算出更高阶的导数（第一，第二，第三，第四等）
and those are quite useful. For example, they’re useful for studying the motion of a particle.
这些非常有用。例如，它们对于研究粒子的运动很有用。
That’s a lot of stuff over here. We talked about higher derivatives, left derivatives, right derivatives.
这里面有很多内容。我们讨论了高阶导数，左导数，右导数。
That’s a whole bag of ideas, and in the next lesson we’ll try and make things look much simpler
那是一整套想法，在下一课中，我们将讨论寻找导数的规则，使事情看起来更简单。
by talking about the rules for finding derivatives. It might all look a little bit difficult right now,
现在可能看起来有点困难，
but once you have rules of derivatives, then things will become much simpler.
但是一旦有了导数规则，事情就会变得简单得多。
That’s for Lesson 9, but before that we will have Problem Session 2 and you can take a small quiz,
这是第9课的内容，但在此之前我们将进行第 2 部分的习题，您可以进行一些小测验，
and that should put you in good shape for Lesson 9. But I’ll stop over here for Lesson 8.